Department of Special Collections, Hesburgh Libraries of Notre Dame
American Colonial Currency Collection
- Continental Currency February 17, 1776Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaContinental CurrencyFebruary 17, 1776, CC 02/17/76; David Hall and William Sellers; Elisha Gallaudet
  - Three Dollars41203 41203, 545; Signers: Adam Hubley, Joel Evans.q
    The first signature is in black ink, while the number and second signature are in reddish brown. The emblem on the front shows an eagle attacking a heron, however, the eagle has pierced the eagle's throat. Encircling the two is the motto, "EXITUS IN DUBIO EST," (The event is uncertain). Franklin, writing under the pseudonym Clericus, described the scene in the September 20, 1775 issue of The Pennsylvania Gazette:The eagle, I suppose, represents Great-Britain, the crane America. This device offers an admonition to each of the contending parties. To the crane, not to depend too much on the ??? of its endeavors to avoid the ??? (by petition, negotiation, and etc.) but prepare for using the means of defense God and nature hath given it; and to the eagle, not to presume on its superior strength, since a weaker bird may wound it mortally.
  - Four Dollars17075 17075, 546; Signers: Philip Kinsey, Thomas Smith
    The first signature and the number are in red, while the second signature is in black. The emblem depicts a wild boar running onto a hunter's spear. The motto reads: AUT MORS AUT VITA DECORA (Death or Liberty).
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the R.M. Smythe collection, auction 234, lot 1302 Dec. 2, 2003.
  - Six Dollars55504 55504, 547; Signers: Samuel Coale (?), John Williams.
    The number and first signature are in red, and the second signature is in black. The emblem depicts a beaver gnawing down a tree with the motto, PERSERVERANDO (By Perseverance).
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the R.M. Smythe collection, auction 234, lot 1303 Dec. 2, 2003.
  - Eight Dollars46560 46560, 578; Signers: Tench Tilghman, James Milligan.
    The number and first signature are in red while the second signature is in black. The seal depicts a harp with an insignia that reads MAJORA MINORIBUS CONSONANT (the larger are in harmony with the smaller).
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from EAHA Auctions, August 23, 2008, lot 70.
- Continental Currency May 9, 1776Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaContinental CurrencyMay 9, 1776, CC 05/09/76; David Hall and William Sellers;
  An emission totaling $5,000,000 payable in Spanish milled dollars or the equivalent in gold or silver, was authorized by the Continental Congress resolutions of May 9th and 27th, 1776. The issue is similar to that of the November 29, 1775 issue except for the bottom border of the front of the $4 reads from left to right toward the bottom of the note, whereas in all other issues it looks upside down and reads toward the center of the bill. Printed by Hall and Sellers in Philadelphia. The paper, made at Ivy Mills in Chester County, Pennsylvania, contained blue fibers and mica flakes. Detector bills were printed on blue paper. Denominations include the: $1, $2, $3, $4, $5, $6, $7 and $8.
  - Two Dollars65856 65856, 428; Signers: Thomas Leech (in red ink), John Howard.; Size: 74 x 96mm (front border design: 70 x 92mm; back border design: 68 x 88mm).
    Numbering and first signature in red ink; second signature in black ink. The emblem on the front shows grain being threshed with a flail and the motto: "Tribulatio ditat" (It is enriched by affliction). The nature print on the back is of raspberry and two filbert leaves and is identical to the nature print used on earlier Pennsylvania currency. Paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    EANA mail bid auction 1/13/96 lot 285. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Three Dollars7170 7170, 429; Signers: George Campbell (in red ink), Josiah Hewes.; Size: 74 x 94mm (front border design: 70 x 92mm; back border design: 68 x 89mm).
    The numbering and first signature are in red ink; the second signature is in red brown. The first signature is somewhat difficult to decipher. There is an upper case G followed by a C with large loops at the top and bottom of the C, there is also a loop as a flourish after the final L. The emblem on the front (39mm) shows an eagle fighting a heron with the motto "Exitus in dubio est" (The outcome is in doubt). On the back is a nature print of skeletonized elm and maple fruit as previously found on Pennsylvania currency. The paper contains blue thread and mica flakes.
  - Six Dollars104224 104224, 430; Signers: Thomas Coombe (in red), Robert Tuckniss.; Size: 73 x 94mm (front border design: 70 x 92mm; back border design: 68 x 90mm).
    Numbered in dark red, first signature in a light red ink and the second signature in a brown ink. The emblem on the front depicts a beaver gnawing down a tree with the motto: "Perseverando" (By perseverance). The nature print on the back displays a buttercup. No image of the back is available. Paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    EANA mail bid auction 8/25/2001 lot 826. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment
  - Seven Dollars133468 133468, 431; Signer: Josiah Hewes (in red ink), Andrew Tybout; Size: 74 x 98mm (front border design: 71 x 93mm; back border design: 68 x 91mm).
    The numbering and first signature are in red ink while the second signature is in brown ink. The emblem on the front shows a storm at sea with the motto: "Serenabit" (It will clear up). The nature print on the back is of a bettercup leaf. the paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    EANA mail bid auction 11/16/96 lot 476. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Eight Dollars23281 23281, 432; Signers: John Howard, Thomas Leech (in red ink).; Size: 75 x 95mm (front border design: 70 x 92mm; back border design: 68 x 90mm).
    The numbering and second signature are in red ink; the first signature is in brown ink. The emblem on the front shows a harp with thirteen strings with the motto: "Majora minoribus consonant" (The larger are in harmony with the smaller). The nature print on the back is of henbit leaf and two buttercup leaves. It is identical to a nature print used on earlier Pennsylvania currency. The paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    EANA mail bid auction 11/16/96 lot 477. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Continental Currency July 22, 1776Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaContinental CurrencyJuly 22, 1776, CC 07/22/76; David Hall and William Sellers;
  An emission totaling $5,000,000 payable in Spanish milled dollars, or the equivalent in gold or silver, was authorized by the Continental Congress resolutions of July 22 and August 13th, 1776. The issue is similar to that of the November 29, 1775 issue except there was no $1 denomination. Apparently this was to be replaced by the Continental Currency coin. It was replaced by a $30 bill similar to that of May 10, 1775. Printed by Hall and Sellers in Philadelphia. The paper, made at Ivy Mills in Chester County, Pennsylvania, contained blue fibers and mica flakes. Detector bills were printed on blue paper. Denominations include the: $2, $3, $4, $5, $6, $7, $8 and $30.
  - Three Dollars77986 77986, 433; Signers: Cornelius Barnes (in red), Jonathan Bayard Smith.; Size: 73 x 97mm (front border design: 70 x 92mm; back border design: 68 x 88mm).
    Numbering and first signature in red ink, the second signature in brown ink. J.B. Smith was a member of the Continental Congress. The emblem on the front (40mm) depicts an eagle fighting a heron with the motto "Exitus in dubio est" (The outcome is in doubt). On the back is a nature print of skeletonized elm and maple fruit as previously found on Pennsylvania currency. The paper contains blue thread and mica flakes.
  - Five Dollars79336 79336, 434; Signers: John Ord, William Webb (in red).; Size: 75 x 96mm (front border design: 70 x 93mm; back border design: 68 x 88mm).
    Numbereing and second signature in red ink, the first signature in brown ink. The emblem on the front (39mm) shows a bleeding hand in a thorn bush with the motto: SUSTINE VEL ABSTINE. The B is an H modified to from a letter B. This is the most difficult emblem in the series to understand. Benjamin Franklin explained the Continental Currency emblems in a letter published under the pseudonym of Clericus in the Pennsylvania Gazette of September 20, 1775. For the five dollar emblem he explained: ...we have a thorny bush, which a hand seems attempting to eradicate. The hand appears to bleed, as pricked by spines. The motto is, SUSTINE VEL ABSTINE; which may be rendered, Bear with me, or let me alone; or thus, Either support or leave me. The bush I suppose to mean America, the bleeding hand Britain. Would to God that bleeding were stopt, the wounds of that hand healed, and its future operations directed by wisdom and equity; so shall the hawthorn flourish, and form an hedge around it, annoying with her thorns only its invading enemies. [B. Franklin, Writings, ed. by J.A. Leo Lemay, 1987, pp. 734-738 on p. 735.The nature print on the back is of betony and sage. The paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
  - Seven Dollars, 435; Signers: John Howard [first signature faded].; Size: 72 x 93mm (front border design: 70 x 91mm; back border design: 67 x 89mm).
    Numbered and first signature in a light red ink that has faded. The emblem on the front shows a storm at sea with the motto: "Serenabit" (It will clear up). The nature print on the back is of buttercup. Paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    EANA mail bid auction 1/13/96 lot 289. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Thirty Dollars51613 51613, 436; Signers: John Howard (faded red ink), Joseph Bullock.; Size: 77 x 100mm (front border design: 70 x 93mm; back border design: 69 x 90mm).
    The numbereing and first signature are in a faded red ink, the second signature is in a brown ink. The emblem on the front (40mm) shows a wreath on a tomb with the motto: "Si recte facies" (If you act righteously). On the back are two emblems: the emblem on the left (40mm) shows a strong wind creating waves and bears the motto: "Vi concitate" (Driven by force); the emblem on the right (39mm) shows the sun shining on sailing ships in a calm sea and bears the motto: "Cessante vento conquiescemus" (When the storm dies down we will rest). The paper contains blue thread and mica flakes.
  - Two Dollars46334 46334, 548; Signers: Nicholas Garrison,
    The number is in faded red ink, the first signature is in black, and the second signature is in reddish brown ink. The emblem is of a hand flailing wheat with the motto TRIBULATIO DITAT (Threshing improves it).
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the R.M. Smythe collection, auction 234, lot 1304. Dec. 2, 2003.
- Continental Currency November 2, 1776Philadelphia, PennsylvaniaContinental CurrencyNovember 2, 1776, CC 11/02/76; David Hall and William Sellers;
  An emission totaling $5,000,000 payable in Spanish milled dollars or the equivalent in gold or silver, was authorized by the Continental Congress resolutions of November 2nd and December 28th, 1776. The issue is similar to that of July 22, 1776. Printed by Hall and Sellers in Philadelphia. The paper, made at Ivy Mills in Chester County, Pennsylvania, contained blue fibers and mica flakes. Detector bills were printed on blue paper. Denominations include the: $2, $3, $4, $5, $6, $7, $8 and $30.
  - Two Dollars31589 31589, 438; Signers: Benjamin Levy (in red), Benjamin Brannan. (Brannon); Size: not available
    The numbering and first signature are in red ink; second signature is in black ink. The emblem on the front shows grain being threshed with a flail and the motto: "Tribulatio ditat" (It is enriched by affliction). The nature print on the back is of a rasberry and two filbert leaves and is identical to a nature print used on earlier Pennsylvania currency. No image of the back is available. The paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    Courtesy of Early American Numismatic Auctions, Inc. Images used with permission from their on-line auction catalog for the auction of April 20, 1996, lot 369.
  - Three Dollars36684 36684, 439; Signers: Hercules Courtenay, Benjamin Brannan (Brannon).; Size: 72 x 92mm (front border design: 70 x 92mm; back border design: 67 x 88mm).
    The first signature is in brown ink; numbering and second signature are in red ink. The emblem on the front (40mm) depicts an eagle fighting a heron with the motto "Exitus in dubio est" (The outcome is in doubt). On the back is a nature print of skeletonized elm and maple fruit. The paper contains blue thread and mica flakes.
  - Four Dollars21835 21835, 440; Signers: Robert Dorsey, Thomas Donnellan.; Size: 75 x 95mm (front border design: 71 x 92.5mm; back border design: 68 x 90mm).
    The numbering and second signature are in red ink; the first signature is in brown ink. The emblem on the front shows a wild boar charging into a spear with the motto: "Aut mors aut vita decora" (Either death or an honorable life). The nature print on the back is of skeletonized maple fruit and is identical to a nature print used on earlier Pennsylvania currency. The paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction 11/16/96, lot 484.
  - Five Dollars18645 18645, 441; Signers: Joshua Barney, Hans Creevey (sometimes Crerry).; Size: 77 x 100mm (front border design: 70 x 92mm; back border design: 68 x 88mm).
    The numbering and first signature are in brown ink; the second signature is in red ink. The emblem on the front (39mm) shows a bleeding hand in a thorn bush with the motto: SUSTINE VEL ABSTINE. The B is an H modified to from a letter B. This is the most difficult emblem in the series to understand. Benjamin Franklin explained the Continental Currency emblems in a letter published under the pseudonym of Clericus in the Pennsylvania Gazette of September 20, 1775. For the five dollar emblem he explained: ...we have a thorny bush, which a hand seems attempting to eradicate. The hand appears to bleed, as pricked by spines. The motto is, SUSTINE VEL ABSTINE; which may be rendered, Bear with me, or let me alone; or thus, Either support or leave me. The bush I suppose to mean America, the bleeding hand Britain. Would to God that bleeding were stopt, the wounds of that hand healed, and its future operations directed by wisdom and equity; so shall the hawthorn flourish, and form an hedge around it, annoying with her thorns only its invading enemies. [B. Franklin, Writings, ed. by J.A. Leo Lemay, 1987, pp. 734-738 on p. 735.]The nature print on the back is of betony and sage. The paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
  - Six Dollars4317 4317, 442; Signers: Theodore Barrell (faded in red), Samuel Hillegas.; Size: 73 x 95mm (front border design: 70mm x (left border trimmed); back border design: 68 x 89mm).
    The numbering and first signature are in a faded red ink; the second signature is in a brown ink. The emblem on the front (39mm) depicts a beaver gnawing down a tree with the motto: "Perseverando" (By perseverance). The nature print on the back displays a buttercup leaf. The paper contains blue thread and mica flakes. On this example the front of the note showns significantly more wear than the back.
  - Eight Dollars59017 59017, 443; Signers: Joseph Gaither, Dennis Griffith (in red ink).; Size: 71 x 96mm (front border design: 70 x 92mm; back border design: 68 x 90mm).
    The numbering and second signature are in red ink; first signature is in black ink. The emblem on the front shows a harp with thirteen strings with the motto: "Majora minoribus consonant" (The larger are in harmony with the smaller). The nature print on the back is of a henbit leaf and two buttercup leaves. It is identical to a nature print used on earlier Pennsylvania currency. The paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction 12/2/95, lot 394.
  - Thirty Dollars37596 37596, 444; Signers: Hercules Courtenay; Benjamin Brannan (Brannon).; Size: 72 x 95mm (front border design: 70 x 91mm; back border design: 69 x 89mm).
    The first signature in black ink; numbering and second signature in red ink. The emblem on the front shows a wreath on a tomb with the motto: "Si recte facies" (If you act righteously). On the back are two emblems: the emblem on the left shows a strong wind creating waves and bears the motto: "Vi concitate" (Driven by force); the emblem on the right shows the sun shining on sailing ships in a calm sea and bears the motto: "Cessante vento conquiescemus" (When the storm dies down we will rest). Paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction 12/2/95, lot 395.
- Continental Currency February 26, 1777Continental CurrencyFebruary 26, 1777, CC 02/26/77; David Hall and William Sellers;
  An emission of $5,000,000 payable in Spanish milled dollars or the equivalent in gold or silver, was authorized by the Continental Congress then meeting in Baltimore because Philadelphia was occupied by British troops. The location of the printers, Hall and Sellers, which had been mentioned on previous issues was left off of this and all subsequent Continental Congress issues. Although this emission is known as the Baltimore issue Newman suspects the bills could have been partly or entirely printed in Philadelphia. This was the last issue to use the phrase "The United Colonies." The paper, made at Ivy Mills in Chester County, Pennsylvania, contained blue fibers and mica flakes. Detector bills were printed on blue paper. Denominations printed were: $2, $3, $4, $5, $6, $7, $8, $30.
  - Three Dollars, 445; Signers: faded; Size: 73 x 96mm (front border design: 70 x 92mm; back border design: 66 x 87mm).
    The emblem on the front depicts an eagle fighting a heron with the motto "Exitus in dubio est" (The outcome is in doubt). On the back is a nature print of skeletonized elm and maple fruit. The paper contains blue thread and mica flakes.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 4/20/96, lot 393.
  - Four Dollars65549 65549, 446; Signers: R. Smith, William Spear.; Size: 74 x 96mm (front border design: 71 x 92mm; back border design: 68 x 90mm).
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 11/16/96, lot 486.
  - Seven Dollars47026 47026, 447; Signers: Rinaldo Johnson, Samuel Stringer Coale.; Size: 74.5 x 95mm (front border design: 71 x 92mm; back border design: 68 x 90mm).
    The numbering and second signature are in red ink; the first signature is in brown ink. The emblem on the front shows a storm at sea with the motto: "Serenabit" (It will clear up). The nature print on the back is of a bettercup leaf. The paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 11/16/96, lot 488.
  - Thirty Dollars Counterfeit27774 27774, 579; Signers: George Welch, Mark Alexander (these signatures are forgeries).
    This counterfeit note has been hole canceled. The number and second signature are in red, and the first signature is in black. The seal depicts a wreath on top of a tomb with the insignia SI RECTE FACIE (if you act righteously).
- Continental Currency May 20, 1777Continental CurrencyMay 20, 1777, CC 05/20/77; ;
  An emission totaling $16,500,000 payable in Spanish milled dollars, or the equivalent in gold or silver, were authorized by ten Continental Congress resolutions passed between May 20, 1777 and April 18, 1778. The issue is similar to that of July 22,1776 with some modifications. The ornament and type fonts for the back of the bills was modified. Also, this was the first issue to use the legend "THE UNITED STATES" replacing the former designation as the United Colonies. Because of extensive British counterfeiting the bills were recalled for an exchange on January 2, 1779 (compare our examples of an original and a counterfeit $8 bill below). However, new bills were not always available and the recall needed to be extended to January 1781! By that date the bills were almost worthless because of hyperinflation (in January 1781 $1 in specie traded for $75 continental in most states, while in Maryland it took $110 continental dollars and in North Carolina $210 continental dollars to obtain $1 in specie). Printed by Hall and Sellers in Philadelphia. The paper, made at Ivy Mills in Chester County, Pennsylvania, contained blue fibers and mica flakes. Detector bills were printed on blue paper. Denominations include the: $2, $3, $4, $5, $6, $7, $8 and $30.
  - Six Dollars30424 30424, 450; Signers: John Taylor (in red), Aquilia Norris; Size: not available
    Numbered and first signature in red, the second signature is in a dark brown ink. The emblem on the front shows a beaver gnawing down a tree with the motto: "Perseverando" (By perseverance). The nature print on the back displays a buttercup. No image of the back is available. Ther paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    Courtesy of Early American Numismatic Auctions, Inc. Images used with permission from their on-line auction catalog for the auction of April 20, 1996, lot 395.
  - Two Dollars75682 75682, 448; Signers: Peter Kurtz, J. Rothrock.; Size: 73 x 98mm (front border design: 70 x 92mm; back border design: 67 x 89mm).
    Numbered and signed in black ink. The emblem on the front shows grain being threshed with a flail and the motto: "Tribulatio ditat" (It is enriched by affliction). The nature print on the back is of raspberry and two filbert leaves and is identical to the nature print used on earlier Pennsylvania currency. Paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    EANA mail bid auction 1/13/96 lot 295. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Three Dollars73784 73784, 449; Signers: William Spear, Thomas Donnellan; Size: 73 x 94mm (front border design: 70 x 93mm; back border design: 66 x 88mm).
    The emblem on the front depicts an eagle fighting a heron with the motto "Exitus in dubio est" (The outcome is in doubt). On the back is a nature print of skeletonized elm and maple fruit. The paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    EANA mail bid auction 4/20/96 lot 393. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Eight Dollars120931 120931, 451; Signers: C. Parr (in red ink), J. Kuhn.; Size: 72 x 95mm (front border design: 69 x 92.5mm; back border design: 68 x 90mm).
    Numbering and first signature in red ink; second signature in black ink. The emblem on the front shows a harp with thirteen strings with the motto: "Majora minoribus consonant" (The larger are in harmony with the smaller). The nature print on the back, though indistinct, is of henbit and two buttercups and is identical to the nature print used on earlier Pennsylvania currency. Paper contains blue threads and mica flakes.
    EANA mail bid auction 1/13/96 lot 299. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Eight Dollars(CF)89127 89127, 452; Signers: S. Elms, George Welsh (these signatures are forgeries).; Size: 72 x 93mm (front border design: 69 x 92mm; back border design: 68 x 89mm).